{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A conservative newspaper in this city was run for years by Colonel Robert McCormick, whose slogan “World’s Greatest Newspaper” was applied to the local radio station, WGN. A paper from this city published the erroneous headline “Dewey Defeats Truman” during the election of 1948. According to legend, Mrs. O’Leary’s cow knocking over a lantern caused a Great Fire in October 1871 in this city. For ten points, name this home of the Tribune, the largest city in Illinois.",
      "answer": "Chicago"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man suggested that his superior, Sir Thomas Fairfax, give up his strong position to encourage a hasty attack by Prince Rupert at the Battle of Naseby. In 1653, this Roundhead dismissed the Rump Parliament, the small group of MPs who remained after Pride’s Purge in 1648. Charles I was beheaded on orders of, for ten points, what leader of the New Model Army, known as “Old Ironsides,” who served as Lord Protector after the English Civil War?",
      "answer": "Oliver Cromwell"
    },
    {
      "question": "Apartment buildings in this city were called insulae, and it contained a sewage system known as the Cloaca Maxima that drained into the Tiber River. This city was built on the Palatine, Capitoline, and five other hills. For ten points, name this ancient city whose entertainment venues included the Circus Maximus and the Colosseum, the capital of a vast Italian empire.",
      "answer": "ancient Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "This work notes that the speaker’s surroundings have been “consecrated [...] far above our poor power to add.” This oration was preceded by a two-hour speech by Edward Everett, and it notes that a “government of the people, by the people, and for the people, will not perish from this earth.” Casualties at a Pennsylvania battlefield were honored with, for ten points, what speech by Abraham Lincoln that opens with the phrase “Four score and seven years ago?”",
      "answer": "Gettysburg Address"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city was sacked two years after the surrender of Alamut fortress by the Assassins. This city was ruled by al-Musta’sim, until he was legendarily killed by being wrapped in a rug and trampled by horses, thereby preventing the shedding of royal blood. In 1258, Hulagu Khan made the Tigris River “run black with ink” after his Mongols sacked, for ten points, what capital of the Abbasid Empire that now serves as the capital of modern Iraq?",
      "answer": "Baghdad"
    },
    {
      "question": "An oratorio by this composer with a libretto based on Genesis and Paradise Lost opens with a “Representation of Chaos.” This composer of The Creation wrote a hymn to Francis II of Austria that is now the national anthem of Germany. The orchestra gradually leaves the stage at the end of a work this man wrote to convince his patron Prince Esterhazy to give his musicians a vacation. For ten points, name this “father of the symphony” and composer of the Farewell Symphony.",
      "answer": "Franz Joseph Haydn"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s Pioneer Park, on top of Telegraph Hill, contains a tower built in memory of Lillie Hitchcock Coit. Its Russian Hill neighborhood is known for a one-block stretch of Lombard Street with eight hairpin turns. This city’s Castro neighborhood was the launching pad for the political career of Harvey Milk. The Haight-Ashbury district nurtured the “hippie” counterculture in, for ten points, what “city by the bay” in Northern California?",
      "answer": "San Francisco"
    },
    {
      "question": "Conspiracy theories about this organization have emerged after the shooting death of Seth Rich in Bloomingdale.DonnaBrazilebecametheinterimleaderofthisorganizationaftertheresignationofDebbie Wasserman-Schulz. Russia may have orchestrated a July 2016 e-mail leak showing this organization’s bias against one of its members, Bernie Sanders. For ten points, name this governing body of the political party that includes Hillary Clinton and Barack Obama.",
      "answer": "Democratic National Committee"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Ledberg Stone probably depicts a wolf devouring a legless man, believed to be a scene from this event. A stone found at Jurby on the Isle of Man might depict the beginning of this event, in which a deity blows the Gjallarhorn. Fimbulwinter precedes this event, according to the Prose Edda. Lif and Lifthrasir are the two humans who survive this event, in which Odin and Thor die. For ten points, name this apocalypse of Norse myth.",
      "answer": [
        "Ragnarok",
        "Fimbulwinter before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s criticism of the Vietnam War led Lyndon Johnson to accuse him of playing “too much football without a helmet.” Though this man signed the Helsinki Accords, he asserted that “there is no Soviet domination of Eastern Europe” during a debate with Jimmy Carter, hampering his re-election bid. For ten points, name this president who succeeded, and controversially pardoned, Richard Nixon.",
      "answer": "Gerald Rudolph Ford or Leslie Lynch King"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This virus’ env gene codes for the gp120 envelope glycoprotein. A disease caused by this virus was briefly, misleadingly called GRID. Using a molecular clock, scientists were able to trace back the origins of this virus to early twentieth century West Africa. This retrovirus infects and lowers the count of helper T cells. Infection by this virus took the lives of Freddie Mercury, Michel Foucault, and Rock Hudson during an explosive epidemic in the 1980s. For ten points, name this virus that causes AIDS.",
        "answer": "HIV or human immunodeficiency virus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A number of HIV and AIDS experts perished aboard this country’s national airline’s Flight 17 when it was shot down above Ukraine in 2014. Another of this country’s planes disappeared over the South China Sea in the same year.",
        "answer": [
          "Malaysia",
          "word forms",
          "Malaysian Airlines"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Panic of 1873 caused the Populist Party and advocates of this resource to push for the Bland-Allison Act. John Sherman proposed an 1890 act doubling the government’s purchasing of this resource. The first major discovery of this resource in the United States was the Comstock Lode in 1859. As a bimetallist, William Jennings Bryan supported the “freeing” of this resource in his “Cross of Gold” speech. For ten points, name this precious metal.",
        "answer": "silver"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Sherman Silver Purchase Act was signed into law under this president, who served between Grover Cleveland’s two terms.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Harrison"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Massive protests in this country began after a speech in Qom during the 15 Khordad Movement. A series of land reforms and pro-Western measures led to further unrest, culminating in a massacre at Jaleh Square on Black Friday. The SAVAK secret police terrorized this nation and executed opponents of its ruler, Mohammed Reza Shah Pahlavi. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern country where a 1979 Islamic revolution was led by Ayatollah Khomeini and flooded the streets of Tehran.",
        "answer": "Islamic Republic of Iran"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Iranian Prime Minister Mohammed Mossadegh was overthrown in an operation backed by the CIA after he threatened to nationalize the assets of this oil company, which was responsible for the Deepwater Horizon spill.",
        "answer": "British Petroleum"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, the Little Willie prototype led to the development of male and female vehicles first used at the Battle of Flers-Courcelette. A plane called the “Scourge” was built during this war after the development of the interrupter. Other vehicles introduced during this war included the Sopwith Camel and the Fokker Dr.I, [d r 1] which was flown by the Red Baron. Tanks and airplanes revolutionized warfare in, for ten points, what early 20th century war, whose trench warfare was called to armistice in 1918?",
        "answer": "World War I or the Great War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This sulfur-containing chemical weapon was used by German forces near Ypres [ee-pruh] in 1917 to disable enemy soldiers. It burned the skin and contaminated the environment.",
        "answer": "mustard gas or sulfur mustard"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The rise of this political ideology was allegorized in the character of Arturo Ui, a mobster created by Bertolt Brecht. Gabriele D’Annunzio’s writings inspired the growth of this ideology, whose rise caused a split in the staff of the socialist newspaper Avanti! in Italy, where it developed during World War I. Bertolt Brecht fled his home country in 1933 in order to escape the rise of, for ten points, what political ideology, espoused in Nazi Germany by Adolf Hitler?",
        "answer": [
          "Fascism",
          "word forms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hitler’s anti-Jewish and anti-communist views were detailed in this two-volume book, written in prison and published in the mid 1920s.",
        "answer": "Mein Kampf or My Struggle"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Man Ray used this medium for dozens of images of Rrose S´elavy, a female alter ego of Marcel Duchamp. A work in this medium shows Florence Owens Thompson with her displaced children and was created by Dorothea Lange. The group f/64 [”f stop 64”] consisted of artists who worked in this medium, including Ansel Adams. Early techniques in this medium were pioneered by Louis Daguerre in the 19th century. For ten points, name this artistic medium created using a camera.",
        "answer": "photography or word forms"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ansel Adams was a native of this state, where he photographed many natural scenes in Yosemite National Park.",
        "answer": "California"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s superiors forced him to agree to the Convention of Cintra; he was later court-martialed for it after his enemy escaped. This man’s victories at Salamanca and Vitoria were key in winning the Peninsular War and defending his ally, Portugal. This general fought Marshal Ney to a standstill at the Battle of Quatre-Bras two days before his troops, alongside Gebhard von Blucher, ended the Hundred Days campaign. For ten points, name this British general who won the Battle of Waterloo.",
        "answer": [
          "Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington",
          "either"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As a diplomat, the Duke of Wellington served as one of the British representatives to this 1815 conference, held to decide the status of Europe after the Napoleonic Wars. It was dominated by Austria’s Prince Metternich.",
        "answer": "Congress of Vienna"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Blaine and Robert Todd Lincoln were witnesses to this event, which took place in the Baltimore and Potomac Railroad Station. The perpetrator of this crime chose a revolver for its ivory handle, which would look good in a museum. The victim of this event survived for over two months, despite the summer heat and incompetent doctors, before he died and was succeeded by a Stalwart. For ten points, name this 1881 crime, committed by Charles Guiteau [ghee-toe], which elevated Chester Arthur to the presidency.",
        "answer": "assassination of James Garfield"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This inventor of the telephone tried to use a rudimentary metal detector to find the bullet in Garfield’s body.",
        "answer": "Alexander Graham Bell"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Space Race",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American space agency that was founded in 1958.",
          "answer": "NASA or the National Aeronautics and Space Administration"
        },
        {
          "question": "Program whose eleventh mission successfully landed the first men on the Moon.",
          "answer": [
            "Apollo Program",
            "Apollo 11"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. President who inspired the race to the Moon with a 1962 speech at Rice University.",
          "answer": "John F. Kennedy or JFK"
        },
        {
          "question": "First successful Soviet satellite, whose launch sparked the race.",
          "answer": "Sputnik 1"
        },
        {
          "question": "First American in space, via the first manned Mercury flight.",
          "answer": "Alan Shepard"
        },
        {
          "question": "Family of rockets that launched American flights to the Moon.",
          "answer": [
            "Saturn family",
            "Saturn V"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet family of rockets, first flown in 1966, which are now the only rockets capable of taking astronauts to the ISS.",
          "answer": "Soyuz"
        },
        {
          "question": "Operation that brought Nazi scientists to work on the American space program.",
          "answer": "Operation Paperclip"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ireland",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Part of the island that remained within the United Kingdom.",
          "answer": [
            "Northern Ireland",
            "Ulster"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Majority religion of the independent Republic of Ireland, putting it at odds with the majority of UK citizens.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of the Republic of Ireland, originally built by Vikings?",
          "answer": "Dublin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Armed movement that fought for Ireland’s independence. Among its branches and offshoots are a Provisional force.",
          "answer": "Provisional Irish Republican Army"
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish political party, led by Gerry Adams, that refuses to sit in Westminster.",
          "answer": "Sinn F´ein"
        },
        {
          "question": "British prime minister and rival of Benjamin Disraeli who tried to pass Home Rule for Ireland.",
          "answer": "William Ewart Gladstone"
        },
        {
          "question": "20th century period of Irish unrest marked by a guerrilla campaign against British forces.",
          "answer": "The Troubles"
        },
        {
          "question": "1998 agreement that led to peace in Ireland, ending the aforementioned unrest.",
          "answer": [
            "Good Friday Agreement",
            "Belfast Agreement"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "James Cook",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Continent in Oceania whose eastern edge he discovered.",
          "answer": "Australia"
        },
        {
          "question": "British scientific organization that sent him to map the transit of Venus.",
          "answer": "Royal Society or the President, Council and Fellows of the Royal Society of London for Improving Natural Knowledge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Research vessel on which he sailed for his first voyage, making the aforementioned discoveries.",
          "answer": "HMS Endeavour"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pacific island chain he discovered and died on, two centuries before it became a U.S. state.",
          "answer": "Hawaii"
        },
        {
          "question": "Disease he prevented in his crew by providing them with Vitamin C.",
          "answer": "scurvy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island mapped by Cook that later merged with Labrador as a Canadian province.",
          "answer": "Newfoundland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Canadian river he mapped during the French and Indian War.",
          "answer": "Saint Lawrence River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where Cook observed the transit of Venus in 1769.",
          "answer": "Tahiti"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The diplomats that negotiated this treaty included Lords Sumner and Cunliffe, the “Heavenly Twins.” This treaty included global recognition of the International Opium Convention and the establishment of the Free City of (20 pts)",
        "Danzig. The issue of Vietnamese indepenence was ignored during its negotiations, despite the pleas of then-student Ho Chi Minh. Article 231 of this treaty, known as the War (10 pts)",
        "Guilt clause, required harsh reparations that were accurately predicted to lead to another war. For ten points, name this treaty, signed in France in 1919, that ended World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "Treaty of Versailles"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The 2010 U.S. Olympic hockey team wore dog tags honoring this action done by Brendan Burke. The Nets’ number 98 jersey became a top-seller after its wearer performed this action, and another man did it after leaving Leeds United for the (20 pts)",
        "L.A. Galaxy in May 2013. A former SEC Defensive Player of the Year for the University of Missouri dropped to the seventh round of the 2014 (10 pts)",
        "NFL draft after performing this action. For ten points, name this action performed by Jason Collins, Robbie Rogers, and Michael Sam when they publicized their sexuality."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "coming out",
        "equivalents like telling people that they are gay"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s former slave and valet, Paul Jennings, wrote a memoir of this man’s time in the White House. After initially vetoing the proposal, this President signed a second bill chartering a second national (20 pts)",
        "bank. As Secretary of State, this man’s refusal to deliver a commission for a judgeship led to the establishment of judicial review. He argued that large republics were better to fend off factionalism in the 10th (10 pts)",
        "Federalist Paper. For ten points, name this “Father of the Constitution” and 4th President of the United States."
      ],
      "answer": "James Madison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, who defined his philosophy in The Story of My Experiments with Truth, signed a pact with Lord Irwin before the Second Round Table Conference to discuss dominion status. This man called for the use of (20 pts)",
        "khadi, or homespun cloth, in opposition to foreign textiles, and he traveled to Dandi to violate a foreign tax during the (10 pts)",
        "Salt March. This man advocated for a form of civil disobedience called satyagraha. For ten points, name this pacifist and leader of the Indian independence movement."
      ],
      "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi or Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Proper acquisition and transfer are meaningful ways of establishing rights according to this concept in Robert Nozick’s Anarchy, State, and Utopia. The idea that inequalities must be rearranged to benefit the least well off is discussed by (20 pts)",
        "John Rawls in a work about this concept. The non-comparative and comparative versions of this concept are often discussed in (10 pts)",
        "criminal law. For ten points, name this philosophical concept often represented by a blindfolded woman holding a set of scales in courtroom sculptures."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "justice",
        "A Theory of Justice"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) On this island, Venetian settlers built a still-standing series of fortifications in Famagusta. A political movement on this island known as enosis sought to (20 pts)",
        "unite it with another country. In 1960, this island gained its independence from the UK, who still controls a military bases at Akrotiri here. A 1974 invasion of this island led to its partition along the (10 pts)",
        "Green Line. For ten points, name this Mediterranean island, divided into a Greek-speaking southern majority and a self-proclaimed “Turkish Republic” in the north."
      ],
      "answer": "Cyprus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man focused on Owen Lattimore in the Tydings Committee hearings, after which his charges were deemed a “fraud and a hoax.” Early in his career, this man fought wartime price controls after receiving a $20,000 personal loan from (20 pts)",
        "Pepsi, earning him the nickname the “Pepsi-Cola Kid.” After he accused the Army of being soft, Joseph Welch asked this man “Have (10 pts)",
        "you no sense of decency?” in Congressional hearings. For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator who claimed there were 205 communists in the State Department during the Red Scare."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph McCarthy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man issued the Decree on Peace, which called for no indemnities or annexations, and passed land reform with the Decree on Land. This man condemned the government in his (20 pts)",
        "April Theses and began a series of economic reforms called the New Economic Policy. Alexander Kerensky’s government was overthrown in the (10 pts)",
        "October Revolution by this man’s forces, who defeated the White Army in the resulting civil war. For ten points, name this leader of the Bolsheviks and founder of the Soviet Union."
      ],
      "answer": "Vladimir Ilyich Lenin or Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov"
    }
  ]
}